Finding Aid for Gilbert and Sullivan Society (University of Michigan) records, 1947-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gilbert and Sullivan Society (University of Michigan) records 1947-2011
University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society.
9 oversize volumes
22.5 linear feet (in 26 boxes)
87182 Bimu F71 2
University of Michigan group established in 1946 devoted to production of Gilbert and Sullivan operettas. Records include production files with programs, photographs, reviews and newspaper clippings, and scattered production notes and memoranda; topical files relating to the Society, its friends organization, and its publication; slides of productions; Society newsletter, "Gasbag"; posters; phonorecords, tapes, and videos of productions.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited with the library beginning in November 1985 by long-time UMGASS member Harry Benford (Donor no. 3123). Additional records were received in 1997 and 1999 through UMGASS (Donor no. 8613 ), and additional sound recordings (audiotapes and discs) and videotapes were received in 2003.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction
The University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (UMGASS) traces its origins to the fall of 1946, when University of Michigan freshman Gloria Katlan (later Bennish) called a campus-wide meeting for those interested in the production of a Gilbert and Sullivan operetta. Organizational concerns occupied the Society's attention for the first year, and it was not until the fall of 1947 that members staged a first performance of the Mikado. Since that date, the Society has produced at least two operettas each year, going through the repertoire of thirteen Gilbert and Sullivan operettas every six or seven years. UMGASS celebrated the 50th anniversary of its founding in 1997.
UMGASS is an officially recognized University of Michigan student organization, but membership is not limited to students. Any interested person may participate in UMGASS productions or hold office in the Society. Under conditions set by its constitution, UMGASS business is managed by a small governing board elected annually by active participants in the productions. The board selects each year's directors and selects and produces the shows. Since 1969, UMGASS has been encouraged and supported by a group called the Friends of the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (FUMGASS). Chief among FUMGASS's activities has been the production of a journal of Gilbert and Sullivan news and events, both on the University of Michigan campus and worldwide. The journal's acronym Gasbag, stands for Gilbert and Sullivan Boys and Girls.
Professor Harry Benford, of the Department of Naval Architecture, and his wife have served as UMGASS faculty advisors since 1956. They were particularly active during the years 1962-1982 and were instrumental in the formation of FUMGASS. Professor Benford served as Gasbag editor from 1969 through 1982, when he and his wife retired from the University.
For further information regarding UMGASS, see their website http://www.umgass.org. The website includes information regarding upcoming operettas and a database of past productions.
The records of UMGASS have been divided into ten series: Slides, Topical Files, Production Files, Posters, Memorabilia Volumes, Magnetic Tape Recordings, Sound Recordings, Audiotapes, Videotapes, and Scrapbooks. Because materials on one production can include photographs, scrapbooks, recordings, or slides- all of which live within different boxes of the collection -- a directory has been compiled in the Production Files series. The directory lists the year and title of the UMGASS production for which the library has materials and a lettered key exists that denotes the physical existence and location of materials within the collection.
Subjects:
Gilbert, W. S. (William Schwenck), 1836-1911--Performances--Michigan.; Sullivan, Arthur, Sir, 1842-1900--Performances--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Gilbert, W. S. (William Schwenck), 1836-1911--Performances--Michigan.; Sullivan, Arthur, Sir, 1842-1900--Performances--Michigan.; Operas and operettas.; Theatrical productions.; University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society.; Gilbert, W. S. (William Schwenck), 1836-1911--Performances--Michigan.; Sullivan, Arthur, Sir, 1842-1900--Performances--Michigan.
Audiocassettes.; CD-ROMs.; Magnetic tapes.; Photographs.; Phonograph records.; Posters.; Slides (photographs); Videotapes.; Sound recordings.
- Slides 1962-1989
  The Slides series (1.75 linear feet) contains slides taken by Harry Benford of UMGASS productions, parties, and weddings from 1962 to 1989. Please note that the production titles are listed in the series Production Files and those productions for which slides were taken are marked with an 'S' to denote their physical existence here.
  - Assorted Productions 1962-1974 (Box 1)
  - Assorted Productions 1974-1989 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (1.0 linear feet) contains files on administrative and organizational aspects of the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (UMGASS), Friends of the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (FUMGASS), and its official publication Gilbert and Sullivan Girls and Boys (Gasbag). The series includes correspondence as well as memoranda, notes and clippings. The files were maintained by Benford and much of the correspondence, especially in the FUMGASS and Gasbag files, is to or from him. (See also the UMGASS Publication Collection Finding aid for actual issues of Gasbag.)
  - FUMGASS
    - Christmas cards circa 1981 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1969-1979 (Box 3)
      - 1980-1984, 2009 (Box 3)
    - Financial records 1973-1984 (Box 3)
    - History; bylaws; procedures 1968-1977 (Box 3)
    - Membership solicitation 1970-1985 (Box 3)
    - Patron list 1969-1978 (Box 3)
    - Scholarships 2009-2010 (Box 3)
  - GASBAG
    - Correspondence
      - 1970-1977 (Box 3)
      - 1978-1984 (Box 3)
  - UMGASS
    - 50th Anniversary Celebration 1997 (Box 3)
    - 60th Anniversary Celebration 2007 (Box 3)
    - 60th Anniversary Planning 2006-2007 (Box 3)
    - Band Show at Football Game 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Complimentary Tickets undated (Box 3)
    - Constitution and By-Laws, undated 1963, 1969, and 1986 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1963-1982 (Box 3)
      - 1975-1985, 1990, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
      - 2010-2011 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence regarding recordings 1993 (Box 3)
    - Executive Board
      - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - 1974-1992, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - G&S Pin undated (Box 3)
    - History 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - Lydia Mendelssohn Theater renovation circa 1977-1980 (Box 3)
    - Membership/Cast Lists 1947-1967 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous reviews 1949-1993 (Box 3)
    - Orchestra Benefit Concert January 31, 2009 (Box 3)
    - P.R. Designs undated (Box 3)
    - Pretty Committee 1990, 2009-2010 (Box 3)
    - Production Dates and Locations 1947-1967 (Box 3)
    - Rehearsal space 1973-1979 (Box 3)
    - Student group policies 1974-1979 (Box 3)
    - Sullivan, Sir Arthur (portrait) 1977-1984 (Box 3)
    - World of Gilbert and Sullivan 1972 (Box 3)
    - 1987, accession: Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Production Files 1947-2010
  The Production Files (5.0 linear feet) series contains information on UMGASS productions from 1947 to 2010. Content varies depending on the production and some are more extensively documented than others; however, information often includes: cast lists, rehearsal schedules, publicity, correspondence, reviews, photographs and playbills (see also the UMGASS Publication Collection finding aid for more playbills). The Production Files series lists all of the productions for which the Bentley Historical Library possesses materials. The items in the series are marked by the following system of letters to denote to the researcher one of two possibilities: 1) The type of materials contained on a production in said folder; or 2) That there are materials on that production elsewhere in the collection outside the physical boxes of the Production Files series (because of size and or format concerns).
  The key to the letters is as follows:
  Po = Posters (located in Box 6 Outsize)
  MTR = Magnetic Tape Recording (located in Box 12)
  R = Sound Recording (located in Boxes 7 to 11, & 13)
  A = Audiotape (located in Box 14)
  V = Videotape (located in Box 14)
  S = Slides (located in Boxes 1 & 2)
  Ph = Photographs (denotes material is in said folder)
  SB = Scrapbook (located in Outsize materials)
  - Unidentified Photographs undated
    - Group Shots (Box 4)
    - Headshots (Box 4)
    - Productions (Box 4)
    - Rehearsals, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1947, Mikado (Box 4)
    [SB, Ph]
  - 1948, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 4)
  - 1948, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph]
  - 1949, Patience (Box 4)
  - 1949, Pirates of Penzance (Box 4)
  - 1950, Iolanthe (Box 4)
  - 1950, Gondoliers (Box 4)
  - 1951, Mikado/Cox & Box (Box 4)
    [SB only]
  - 1951, Ruddigore (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph; R]
  - 1952, Princess Ida (Box 4)
  - 1952, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 4)
    [Ph; SB]
  - 1953, H.M.S. Pinafore/Trial by Jury (Box 4)
    [SB]
  - 1953, Patience (Box 4)
    [SB; R]
  - 1954, Thespis/Sorcerer (Box 4)
    [SB; MTR]
  - 1954, Pirates of Penzance (Box 4)
    [SB, Ph; MTR]
  - 1955, Iolanthe/Cox & Box (Box 4)
  - 1955, Gondoliers (Box 4)
  - 1956, Mikado (Box 4)
  - 1956, Ruddigore (Box 4)
  - 1957, Princess Ida (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph; MTR]
  - 1957, Trial by Jury/Sorcerer (Box 4)
    [SB; MTR, Ph]
  - 1958, H.M.S. Pinafore/Cox & Box (Box 4)
  - 1958, Patience (Box 4)
  - 1959, Pirates of Penzance (Box 4)
  - 1959, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph; R; MTR]
  - 1960, Iolanthe (Box 4)
    [SB; R; MTR]
  - 1960, Mikado (Box 4)
  - 1961, Ruddigore/Trial by Jury (Box 4)
  - 1961, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 4)
    [SB; R; MTR; Ph]
  - 1962, Patience (Box 4)
  - 1962, Princess Ida (Box 4)
    [SB; S; MTR; Ph]
  - 1963, Cox & Box/ Toledo War (Box 4)
    [SB; S]
  - 1963, Gondoliers (Box 4)
    [SB; S; Ph; MTR]
  - 1963, Mikado (Box 4)
  - 1964, Iolanthe (Box 4)
  - 1964, Trial by Jury/Sorcerer (Box 4)
  - 1965, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 4)
    [SB; S; R; MTR]
  - 1965, Pirates of Penzance (Box 4)
    [SB; R; MTR, Ph]
  - 1966, Ruddigore (Box 4)
  - 1966, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 4)
  - 1967, Patience (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph; R; S; MTR]
  - 1967, Mikado (Box 4)
    [SB; Po; S; R; MTR]
  - 1968, Princess Ida (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph; R; S]
  - 1968, Oliver! (Box 4)
    [SB; Po; R; S]
  - 1968, Gondoliers, 2 folders (Box 4)
    [SB; R; S; Ph]
  - 1969, Iolanthe (Box 4)
  - 1969, Paint Your Wagon (Box 4)
    [SB; Po; S]
  - 1969, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 4)
    [SB; S; Ph]
  - 1970, Pirates of Penzance (Box 4)
  - 1970, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 4)
    [SB; Po; S; R; Ph]
  - 1971, Ruddigore (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph; Po; R; S]
  - 1971, Thespis (Box 4)
  - 1971, Mikado (Box 4)
    [SB; Ph; Po; S]
  - 1972, Patience (Box 4)
  - 1972, H.M.S. Benford (Box 4)
  - 1972, Gondoliers (Box 4)
    [SB; Po; R; S; Ph]
  - 1973, Haste to the Wedding (Box 4)
  - 1973, Princess Ida (Box 4)
  - 1973, Grand Duke (Box 4)
  - 1974, Iolanthe (Box 4)
  - 1974, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 4)
  - 1975, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 4)
  - 1975, Pirates of Penzance (Box 4)
    [SB; Po; S; R]
  - 1976, Ruddigore (Box 5)
  - 1976, Sorcerer (Box 5)
  - 1977, Mikado (Box 5)
    [SB; Po; S; Ph]
  - 1977, Patience (Box 5)
    [S; R]
  - 1978, Gondoliers (Box 5)
    [Po; S; R; Ph]
  - 1978, Princess Ida (Box 5)
  - 1979, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 5)
    [Ph; S; R]
  - 1979, An Evening with Gilbert and Sullivan (Box 5)
  - 1979, Trial by Jury (Box 5)
    [Po; S]
  - 1979, Iolanthe (Box 5)
    [S; A]
  - 1980, Pirates of Penzance (Box 5)
    [S; A; Ph; Po; MTR]
  - 1980, Ruddigore (Box 5)
    [Po; S; Ph; MTR]
  - 1981, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 5)
    [Po; S; Ph; A]
  - 1981, Utopia Limited (Box 5)
    [Po; S; Ph; R]
  - 1982, Patience (Box 5)
    [S, A; MTR; Ph]
  - 1982, Gondoliers (Box 5)
    [Po; Ph]
  - 1983, Mikado (Box 5)
    [Po; Ph; A]
  - 1983, Sorcerer (Box 5)
    [S; Po; MTR; Ph]
  - 1984, Iolanthe [MTR; Ph] (Box 5)
  - 1984, Princess Ida (Box 5)
    [S; MTR; A; Po; Ph]
  - 1985, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 5)
    [MTR; S; Ph]
  - 1985, Grand Duke (Box 5)
    [Po]
  - 1986, Pirates of Penance (Box 5)
  - 1986, Trial by Jury/Cox & Box (Box 5)
  - 1986, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 5)
    [Po; S; A]
  - 1987, Ruddigore (Box 5)
  - 1987, Patience (Box 5)
    [Ph; Po; S]
  - 1987, "Here's a Howdy Do" (Box 5)
  - 1988, Gondoliers (Box 5)
    [Po; A; Ph]
  - 1988, Utopia Limited, 2 folders (Box 5)
    [S; Po; V; Ph]
  - 1989, Mikado (Box 5)
    [Po; Ph; V]
  - 1989, 40th Anniversary (Box 5)
    [Poster only]
  - 1989, Sorcerer (Box 5)
    [Po; Ph; MTR]
  - 1990, Iolanthe (Box 5)
  - 1990, Princess Ida (Box 5)
    [Po; Ph; A; V]
  - 1991, H.M.S. Pinafore (Box 5)
  - 1991, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 5)
  - 1992, Ruddigore (Box 5)
    [Po; V; Ph]
  - 1992, Pirates of Penzance (Box 5)
    [Po; V]
  - 1993, Gondoliers (Box 5)
  - 1993, Trial by Jury/Cox & Box (Box 5)
  - 1993, Patience (Box 5)
  - 1994, Mikado (Box 5)
  - 1994, Sorcerer, 1994 (Box 5)
  - 1995, H.M.S. Pinafore, 1994 (Box 5)
  - 1994, 1995, Grand Duke (Box 16)
    [Po; A; V; Ph]
  - 1996, Iolanthe, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - 1996, Yeomen of the Guard, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - 1997, Pirates of Penzance (Box 16)
  - 1997, Princess Ida (Box 16)
  - 1998, Ruddigore (Box 16)
  - 1998, Patience (Box 16)
  - 1999, Gondoliers (Box 16)
  - 1999, Utopia, Limited (Box 16)
    [Po; Ph
  - 2000, Mikado (Box 16)
  - 2000, Sorcerer (Box 16)
  - 2001, HMS Pinafore, 2 folders (Box 16)
    [MV; Ph; Po]
  - 2001, Grand Duke [ (Box 16)
    Po; Ph]
  - 2002, Iolanthe (Box 16)
  - 2002, Engaged (Box 16)
    [Ph; MV; Po]
  - 2002, Yeomen of the Guard (Box 17)
  - 2003, Pirates of Penzance (Box 17)
  - 2003, Ruddigore (Box 17)
  - 2004, Princess Ida (Box 17)
    [Po; MV; Ph]
  - 2004, The Gondoliers (Box 17)
    [Ph; Po]
  - 2005, Patience (Box 17)
  - 2005, Sorcerer (Box 17)
  - 2006, Mikado (Box 17)
  - 2006, Cox and Box; Trial by Jury (Box 17)
    [MV]
  - 2006, H.M.S Pinafore (Box 17)
  - 2007, The Grand Duke (Box 17)
    [MV; Po]
  - 2007, Iolanthe (Box 17)
  - 2007, The Yeoman of the Guard (Box 17)
  - 2008, Ruddigore (Box 17)
  - 2009, The Pirates of Penzance (Box 17)
  - 2009, Patience (Box 17)
  - 2010, The Gondoliers (Box 17)
- Posters 1967-2007
  The Poster series (1.0 linear feet & One Outsize Folder) is comprised of posters advertising UMGASS productions covering the years from 1967 to 2007. (Please note that the production titles are listed in the series Production Files and those productions for which posters were made are marked with a 'Po' to denote their physical existence here.)
  - Assorted Productions 1967-2007 (Box 6)
- Memorabilia Volumes 2001-2007
  The Memorabilia Volumes series (1.5 linear feet), 2001-2007, contains binders prepared by Marilyn Gouin UMGASS costume designer. The binders include sketches for costumes, cast lists, thumbnail photographs and digital photographs on CDs from the various operettas featuring the costumes. [See Production Series for titles]
  - Assorted Productions 2001-2005 (Box 14)
  - Assorted Productions 2006-2007 (Box 15)
- Magnetic Tape Recordings (Reel-to-Reel) 1954-1989
  The Magnetic Tape Recordings series (9.5 linear feet) is comprised of reel-to-reel magnetic tape recordings of UMGASS productions for the years 1954 to 1989. (Please note that the production titles are listed in the series Production Files and those productions for which magnetic recordings were made are marked with an 'MTR' to denote their physical existence here).
  - Assorted Productions 1954-1955 (Box 18)
  - Assorted Productions 1956-1958 (Box 19)
  - Assorted Productions 1958-1959 (Box 20)
  - Assorted Productions 1960-1961 (Box 21)
  - Assorted Productions 1962-1963 (Box 22)
  - Assorted Productions 1963-1965 (Box 23)
  - Assorted Productions 1967-1968 (Box 24)
  - Assorted Productions 1980-1985 (Box 25)
  - Assorted Productions 1989 undated (circa 1980-1989) (Box 26)
- Sound Recording Discs 1951-1981
  The Sound Recording Discs series (3.0 linear feet) contains recordings of UMGASS productions from 1951 to 1981. (Please note that the production titles are listed in the series Production Files and those productions for which sound disc recordings were made are marked with an 'R' to denote their physical existence here.)
  - Assorted Productions 1951-1958 (Box 7)
  - Assorted Productions 1959-1966 (Box 8)
  - Assorted Productions 1967-1969 (Box 9)
  - Assorted Productions 1970-1973 (Box 10)
  - Assorted Productions 1973-1975 (Box 11)
  - Assorted Productions 1976-1981 (Box 12)
- Audiotapes (Cassettes) 1979-1995
  The Audiotapes series (.5 linear feet) includes recordings from UMGASS productions from 1979 to 1995. (Please note that the production titles are listed in the series Production Files and those productions for which audiotape recordings were made are marked with an 'A' to denote their physical existence here.)
  - Assorted Productions 1979-1995 (Box 13)
- Videotapes (VHS) 1988-1996
  The Videotape series (.5 linear feet) consists of recordings from UMGASS productions from 1988 to 1996. (Please note that the production titles are listed in the series Production Files and those productions for which videotape recordings were made are marked with a 'V' to denote their physical existence here.)
  - Assorted Productions 1988-1996 (Box 13)
    (includes undated, tape of The Yeomen of the Guard)
- Scrapbooks 1947-1977
  The Scrapbooks series (9 bound volumes) contains several scrapbooks maintained by the society containing of clippings, production reviews, photographs, and playbills for operettas produced from 1947 to 1977.
  - Volume 1 1947-1949 (Volume 1)
  - Volume 2 1950-1952 (Volume 2)
  - Volume 3 1953-1955 (Volume 3)
  - Volume 4 1955-1958 (Volume 4)
  - Volume 5 1958-1964 (Volume 5)
  - Volume 6 1964-1969 (Volume 6)
  - Volume 7 1969-1973 (Volume 7)
  - Volume 8 1973-1977 (Volume 8)
  - Volume 9 1958-1960 (Volume 9)
Related Material
Other collections of interest include the personal papers of Gloria Bennish, founder of the society and the UMGASS Publication Collection, which includes publications produced by the society. See the finding aids for these collections for further information.